Start recording.
OK, You start.
Yeah, Yeah, it started.
Yeah.
All right, let's go for it.
OK,
so we are talking about a scenario where
there are multiple source objects, OK,
Be it for the history data or for
incremental where the data is loaded into
the history bucket tables.
OK,
you know the difference between the
current bucket and the history bucket,
right?
Current bucket will reflect what is there
in SOR whereas in history bucket any
change that would have happened would
come and get added as an appended record.
It won't overwrite it.
They are not merging the data rather they
will append it Yeah but in in the in the
history bucket we would it would be a one
time load yes.
So there why is are we even talking about
appended record?
Because the day we execute the history,
the history bucket.
Sorry, sorry,
let me that's where I was asking about
the current bucket and history bucket
difference.
Are you aware of because in zone 1 you
have current bucket and history bucket,
OK,
Within history you again have two
subsections 1 is S4 specific history and
the legacy which is the Teradata history.
OK, OK.
This is how it is segregated, OK,
But now but we are sorry, sorry,
sorry Narika,
but question legacy we in our history
load we should be using the legacy 3D
bucket now, Yes.
And that's where before going to the
scenario in the beginning, I mentioned,
right,
like this is something that will apply be
it for the history only or even for the
incrementals in both the scenarios,
he will face this challenge.
OK, OK.
And here I mean,
based on all the joins and all that we
have done so far, right,
what has happened is there would have
been a driving table, OK.
And that was left joined with other
tables to get your target data.
So while doing this what happens we were
taking the row effective and expiration
dates like whatever changes have happened
to the driving table that was giving us
what should be the row effective and
expiration date in the target.
Because the left join with this table is
only giving us additional attribute
information to it and then we are loading
into the target.
Whereas the scenario that we are going to
talk about is it is not a left join,
rather it could be an inner join or full
outer join sort of where both play equal
role in identifying the versions in the
target table.
OK, table Table 1 is the source table.
Yeah,
even driving table is also a source table.
OK, OK.
Driving table is a source table and
you're joining with the table one.
At times it can also be a type list table
or something else in the source itself.
OK.
When you do with the type list table,
type list is like a reference data, right?
Those cases that will not drive your row
effective dates in the target,
rather only the driving table changes is
what you will use or what did I when was
it updated or what is the effectiveness
of the record that will be used in
generating the row effective and
expression dates in the target?
Yeah, yeah.
Whereas when we come to other scenarios,
there are cases where you will have to
look at when did my driving table, I mean,
in this case,
it's not like a driving table,
Both are having equal preference.
OK, consider Table 2 and table three,
got it.
So both has almost equal preference.
Any change in Table 2 or any change in
Table 3 both should have the impact on
the target version that we have
maintained.
Correct, Correct.
OK, correct.
That is the scenario that we are talking
about.
So for this,
how would we even generate those row
effective and expiration dates is what I
wanted to show you with an example here.
And we need Nikhil's help in getting that
query built.
So this is a pattern that we are trying
to implement, yes,
for all the assets where wherever we have
join with multiple driving tables.
Second scenario is effectively multiple
driving table.
Do we have any assets who are have tables
like that?
I think there would be some, yeah, yeah.
Currently,
MVP team has one example where they are
building it,
but Abhi has taken it as a point to give
us the list of what objects has those and
where.
I mean,
even though team might have earlier
provided multiple history table objects
to be used,
he's going to revisit it and confirm
whether we are really going to have it.
If we are having multiple history tables,
are all of those contributing to the
effective date search changes here?
Or is it only one table that is
contributing so that segregation of which
scenario applies to which target table is
going to be provided by data modules?
OK, OK, yeah.
Now let us get into the example.
But here table one,
I'm just considering that you had changes
of two days received at once or maybe the
first time when you are loading.
Also there is a possibility that he would
have multiple entries for the same key
column right?
The versions source is storing them as
type 2.
This is how you could receive the records
like this is a key.
I'm just saying on day one I received
this data.
By that time I had two versions of that
K1 key which is having value A during
10th September to 21st September and then
I'm having value B which is valid from
21st September to higher day.
OK in Table 2 on day one,
I had only one specific version for that
K1 got it here.
Consider K1 is something that I can use
to join these two tables OK, correct,
correct.
So OK Table 2 has value P and this value
is valid from 9th September onwards.
OK so in target table I need to get this
attribute value,
the nonkey value and this nonkey value as
well.
So I'm going to use both the tables to
prepare my target table.
What will be in my target table?
I need to come up with the row effect 2
and expiration dates with the non key
value from Table 1 and non key value from
Table 2 as well for that key, right?
So yeah, when I load the data,
what should be my data set in the target
day one?
What when I yeah, go ahead.
No, no, no, no, no, please,
please continue.
I'm with you.
Yeah, Day one when we load the records,
when we look at these two combinations,
what happens when I join this 10th
September to 21st September with this
record,
I'm going to get this 9th September to
high end date is the validity of this one,
right?
Which means from 9th September when the
value was P until 10th September,
there was no entry in table one, right?
So that is where if you see 9th September
to 10th September now.
Now one question, sorry Nidhika,
I'm just asking as and when I it.
Yeah, no worries.
Yeah, go ahead.
So now when we join these two tables,
so we are getting we are in table one,
we are getting 2 records,
but we have to maintain history for both
like we need to have both of them in the
target.
Yes, OK.
OK.
So but basically then we have to versions,
right?
For each of the version,
we have to still get the data into the
target,
but then the date should also be part of
the equation in the target table.
Yeah,
like K as a key under row effective date
generally creates the uniqueness.
OK.
But in this case, correct,
you have K1 with 9th September,
K1 with 10th September,
K1 with 21st September, 3 different yeah,
combinations.
So it will be like it is not a inner join.
Definitely it is a join.
It's a outer join on K1 between 2 tables.
I mean, it can be inner join also, right?
Even when you do an inner join this
record effectively meaning sorry, sorry,
sorry, I'm interrupting, you know,
and you know, like stepping over issues.
But in in this case,
Table 2 because it's only one record
which is effective for both the records
of table one,
then this the join should be at the both
and then the dates here should be in the
target table should be 9th September at
to high end date because that's a record.
We'll we should put the the larger value
right in terms of date.
Yeah.
But if you see the table one values value
A for this K1 is valid only between 10th
September to 21st, 11 days.
Got it, Got your point.
Yeah.
OK, so that's where if you see this data,
you'll get the idea of what is expected.
Yeah.
From 9th to 10th,
I don't have anything from table one,
but Table 2, it has the value as speed.
Got it.
Oh, so it'll it'll have two like go,
go record by record, identify scenarios,
identify scenarios, right.
Like indirectly,
first you are getting all the effective
dates from here and then you need to
split like, OK,
this is from 9th September from Table 2.
It'll be a row by row operation.
Then yeah, the join, the join that we do.
I don't know if sequel can sequel,
there is no sequel function which can
create these scenarios like we have
depicted exactly what I asked.
That's what it will be a cursor,
cursor thing or you know,
record by record logic that there there
is a way to do it.
You'll have to write like a multiple CTS,
multiple CTS to be used.
Yeah, multiple CTS and window functions.
Yeah, multiple CTS.
And also like once you do this again,
the deduplication logic,
whatever we are doing,
even that has to be accounted for to make
sure there are no duplicates immediately
and then make sure we are consolidating
the dates again if there are any
duplicates.
But like,
suppose if this was also a for any reason,
because sometimes the data here,
right there can be some other column
value which has changed and this did not
change as such.
OK, got it.
Yeah.
This is what we need Nikhil to figure out
basically.
Now if it's like one time problem,
if like you depicted,
like if you if you create scenarios,
then writing sequel should be easy once
we understand the flow, sequel generation,
you know,
either we get window functions or CTS or
we'll go into PL.
I mean, programming logic.
Yeah, OK.
So with the data that we already had,
this is how your data would look like on
day one,
like 9th to 10th and nothing from table
one.
But you have from Table 2,
this is what you have.
Then 10th to which date should we go?
The immediate next date that we have is
21st September, right?
So 10th to 21st September is what we are
creating.
So what is the value that is valid
between 10th to 21st September from table
one, it is A whereas in Table 2,
it is feed, right?
So that's what we have here.
The next one is 21st September to high
end date combination.
So for this one,
when we look at Table 2 again,
it is just one single entry,
it is P whereas here it is B.
So B&P is what we have here.
Got it.
And for these records,
when we insert on day one,
the east delete flag in the table should
be left as.
So by default blank,
blank or whatever team is following
currently, that's what we have to go with,
OK,
We won't keep Y for any of these records.
Is delete is like a soft delete marker of
the record.
So what is the purpose of is delete like
how we'll have to figure out how is
delete is populated in the current system.
Yeah, yeah.
In in what we what we have in our tables.
Yes,
currently team is already implementing.
I'm not sure if they're defaulting it to
in or they're leaving it as NULL.
OK, OK, whatever is the current default,
that is what we'll follow for all these
tables.
Who has this logic implemented?
It's the MVP team or it's the no,
our MVP doesn't have.
They came up with this scenario asking
how should we design it.
I will explain them as well.
OK.
But OK,
if we can get help in expediting on
creating this right?
Because Yeah, yeah,
I would want to retain MVPT people on our
team if there's this much involvement.
I mean, Ramnik is too good, man.
Told me.
At least the way she identifies problems
or ask the questions,
she puts her thought and that comes up.
OK, Sure.
Yeah, yeah, I done that.
Told me about that.
Yeah.
Now coming to this day 2 scenario.
No.
OK,
what happened on day one I had both the
tables with changes right?
Day 2 it's really not necessary that I
have a change, just a second.
Yeah,
on day 2 we have change only to the Table
2, not Table 1.
OK, so here what is happening,
because the source is maintaining them as
a SCD type 2,
we are going to receive the changes.
Sometimes it can be just one single
version or it can be multiple versions
also, right?
They're accounting for the worst case
scenario where sometimes you may have to
load the data from source after a day or
two.
OK.
So that's why I have considered that we
received multiple versions for that key
on day 2 with the changes effective from
9 September to 15 September 1 version,
which is like whatever we had earlier,
we are just expiring it because we have a
change.
Then the reason this is expired is we
have one more change which is created
with the value Q and then we had R like
multiple changes happened on the same day.
Like 2 changes earlier we had P but then
they changed it to Q and then they
changed it to R OK, OK.
This is scenario 2 basically.
I mean,
this is all for the same combinations
itself.
The first one we just took.
OK, how will my data look like, right?
Yeah.
Now when yeah, this change happens,
this is where the complexity arises, OK?
Like yesterday you already loaded this
data into the target.
OK,
Today Table 1 is not going to have any
additional changes for K1, however,
so able to sorry, sorry,
we got to break the flow.
Just one question.
Row #29 is another scenario for Table 2,
right?
Yes.
And just the next day we are receiving
updates.
Yeah, but OK, OK, no, no next day.
OK, we, we get so,
So what I'm saying till row #27 if we
execute that load on say 21st September,
that's that's the,
that's the picture day one,
day one in column H is 21st September,
right?
That's what we are trying to say.
OK,
if you're talking about what day one
means, consider 21st September also.
But here then in that case,
the dates I have provided might not
exactly align.
Maybe I can just keep it that way here
also.
No, no, no, update 21st.
I want to,
I want to make sure that our scenarios
are separate scenario.
Day one is a separate scenario.
Day one does not add up to does not
contribute to the situation in day 2.
Or do you think that's the case?
Day one does not contribute.
It's the same thing, Pratik.
It does.
So it's the same key.
The rows are the same.
It's the same keys.
So it's just that on day 2,
you got some updates to the data.
It's just OK that you got new records.
So got it, got it.
So day 2,
we are building up what we had on day one.
Yes,
Day 2 is basically new records coming for
the same keys.
So now we have to figure out how day one
and day two data will be combined in the
final table for us.
Consider it's like incremental data,
right?
Yeah, that is coming from SOS.
Yeah, first day you received this,
the next day you are receiving additional
changes only for one of the table,
not for the other table or maybe even.
Yeah, this also can help.
But here I just mocked up for one
scenario where you are receiving changes
only to Table 2,
but not necessarily table one.
Now what happens this Table 2 is having
multiple versions here.
But if you see the information here,
this is a split from 9 September to 15
September and 15 September to 22nd
September, 22nd to high end date.
Now if you look at the data here,
you have already loaded data for 9th
September to 10th September and 10th to
21st.
Right now all of this has to get
revisited.
The reason whatever you had for 9th
September until 10th September, yes,
the information was still valid.
So it is fine.
You don't have to touch this record.
Whereas if you see for here,
based on this,
what you would have created,
9th September to 15th September is there,
but 10th September record exists.
9th to 10th would be your first.
Yeah.
Combination then.
No, I get it.
I understand.
Yeah, I get it.
We'll have to go row by row.
But then this is a PL.
sequel operation.
This is a row by row operation because
for every combination we have to check
table one.
How is Table 2?
Then we have to go to the target.
Then we have to update those records in
the target or modify the records in the
target.
It's a concern that is we want,
but you too.
Listen out one more thing please and then
we will come to that.
Sorry, sorry to sorry, sorry,
please go ahead.
Oh no, no, just,
I mean whatever you are saying is correct.
It's just that the way we are thinking of
designing it is instead of going and
updating that record,
just soft delete those records if there
has been a change on it.
Like if you see in this case even that I
get it because sorry,
sorry I'm interrupting,
but I totally get it.
Now we soft delete the old records and we
insert the new record and that's why we
have this is delete filter.
Yes.
But I'm saying this will have a
performance implication because now we
will go row by row.
We have to 1st identify which records
have you know in the source have changed.
We have to implement this using cursor
based approach because I don't think it
can be handled through you know like
window operations or sequel operations or
CTS.
Because we are we are going row by row
for every combination of target Table 1
and Table 2 we have to identify,
go to the target,
make some updates then insert.
So it's a row by row operation now and
that will slow us down.
Performance implication will be there
because there might be a performance
implication for this one, Pratik,
which is OK, yeah,
let's figure out right what I, yeah,
want with at the end of the day,
it has to be handled somehow in SQL.
Yeah, yeah.
No, no, no, I'm, I'm not not,
I'm not pushing back on that front,
just that.
And I think for this for cursors,
the best approach is to write a procedure.
I am not really sure if we can do this in
let's say if we can avoid procedure,
if we can have multiple options that'll
that'll be OK.
Only we'll go with procedure if there is
a significant gain of performance because
procedure logic is compiled that that's
why we.
Yeah, I know,
I know they they don't want stored proxy
in their.
OK, yeah, OK, OK, OK.
Actually procedures would have been
better.
These guys are putting taking their
entire logic and putting it in
informatical in a flat pipeline.
Yeah,
that is the worst kind of architecture
that I've seen.
Yeah,
because whole point of using they should
have been procedures actually they should
not have yes, IDM.
So it should IDM they should have just
been calling procedures.
No sequel in there, but it is what it is.
The whole point of using a detailed tool
is to make sure that you can see the
logic visually.
Here the you are using that tool.
Basically, you are using, you know,
fighter jet to kill mosquitoes.
But it's fine.
It is.
Yeah.
What it is.
Sorry, Nidhika, but I understand.
Yeah.
If you want to explain, please do.
I mean,
because Nikhil has to understand this,
right?
If he has to, right.
So that's where I'm trying to Yeah, yeah,
yeah.
The thought here, yeah, yeah, yeah,
please.
Sorry.
So yeah, Day 2,
when you create this 9th to 10th,
you're not going to add any new record
because there has been no change to that
particular version,
whereas the 10th September to 21st
September has to be split.
Now the reason being here,
the value of P is valid only until 15th
September 15th, right.
So whatever we had from 10th to 21st,
now we are going to create one for 10th
to 15th and 15th to 21st as two different
versions.
Reason being this data if we see the
first one is valid with P value,
the second one will have Q as the value
in it.
OK.
And again from 21st to 22nd,
the reason is here Q is valid until 22nd
and then you have a different high end
value.
So you can't have this until high end.
You need to split that also from 21st to
22nd and then 22nd to high end date.
Got it.
So indirectly,
the combinations here that we would see
is these are all the pointers, right?
These are the effective date combinations
that will come out of it.
Using this it we sort and see 9th
September to 15th September is what we
had, but 10th September is the next value,
so 9th September to 10th September,
then 10th September after that which is
the next value 15th September.
So 10th to 15th, then 15th to 21st,
21st to 22nd and then high end.
OK.
That's how it has to be formulated to
come up with these dates and what value
should go in each of those.
Got it.
And currently in the other scenario,
right, which we discussed initially,
like there is a driving table and left
join with others,
we were reading only the delta data of
the driving table and all the data of the
second table from the current bucket,
whereas the delta data of the driving
table from the history bucket.
That used to be our majority of the
patterns.
Or the second table would have been your
zone 2 table, not the zone 1 table.
That's how we were generating it.
But for this one,
even though there is no change in table
one data,
still we need to account for all the
records related to that key where we
received a change in Table 2 and vice
versa.
OK.
And yeah,
when we are doing this now for the 10th
September on day one,
I already had an entry right This one I
will have to mark it as is deleted on day
two.
Yeah, on day two, yes.
So both of these two will have is delete
flag.
Why?
The reason is 10th to 21st is no longer
valid as it is being split into 10th to
15th and 15th to 21st and this one is
also no longer valid as there has been a
change with the expiration date and this
one.
So so this I get it,
this logic will be applied to every type
to a CD table, no?
That's where I was saying right?
Like when you are having multiple source
tables and both from the history bucket
and both are contributing to the
effective and expiration dates in the
target.
Only in that scenario we need to build
this kind of logic.
You may still have scenarios where
multiple history bucket tables are used,
or maybe 1 history bucket table is used
and restore from the current bucket
tables.
In that case,
mostly your driving table is going to
define what should be your effective and
expiration dates.
No, no,
here we are storing the history in the
target.
So that's a target 2 history type 2 SCD
table, right?
If the target table was type 1 SCD,
then we did not have anything of this
sort.
That is right.
So it I am trying to see I'm trying to
cover that point that not all type 2 STD
tables will be there but certain type
type 2 STD tables where we have scenarios
like we're driving tables as are as you
mentioned only those tables will have.
So it's this logic will this scenario
complex scenario will not go for
performance wise.
I'm trying to run in the mind that,
you know, not all tables,
it's it'll be like very few tables which
will have this scenario like this.
Yeah, that is right.
Very few tables should have this.
That's where Abhi just message saying
that he will validate and confirm on that.
Yeah.
OK, OK, OK, OK.
But at least for this we need to come up
with how the query can be formed so team
can build it using that patterns.
Yeah, yeah.
And this will be valid both for
historical data in and incremental data.
Yeah, no.
Even in history there could be such
scenarios where multiple history tables
which are currently loaded as sed type 2
or even 1 is type 1 and the other is type
2.
But both of them can contribute to the
versions like that legacy history you're
talking about, right?
Even there they may end up with scenarios.
No, no, I get it.
Yeah,
Yesterday only I asked Nikhil to validate
the queries with Sumantha's writing.
So this goes this goes into that also.
And who figured this out?
Who figured this out?
Did you figure this out or did we like
testing something?
Deepankar and Ramnik, they came to me.
I mean,
I won't know right until someone tells me
this is what we are.
Yeah.
Having.
Yeah.
So they came to me.
But this is something we already knew
that this scenario can happen because,
yeah, Bogdan appraised this one.
So saying that you are going to have
these kind of scenarios and they have
implemented this like Bogdan's team has
implemented in AW WC, if I'm not wrong,
where the claimant,
claimant data is being received in this
fashion.
So they have to go and revisit and update
the timelines.
I mean,
the effectiveness of the records with it.
OK.
Yeah.
So we were aware of it and now the
pattern came up based on what MVP team
was doing.
So we have to solve it because even
though we know,
we don't know how the data model is
changing, right?
That's where we did not spend time on
this until we have variables.
OK, OK.
Yeah.
And Deepankar asked this primarily,
I think he's doing the development of one
of the table where they're having these
tables.
So he asked for clarity how to join this.
OK, OK, sure.
OK.
With this being said, Pratik,
we should also look at any history that
our team is loading.
Do they see this kind of scenario like
multiple source tables with type 2
loading into one single target?
And are those type 2 tables,
both of them contributing to those dates?
OK, OK.
Yep.
Sure.
Sure, Navika.
Yeah.
Because their query patterns will change
now.
Yeah, Yeah.
And it's it's it's not simplistic.
It is.
It's a whole different level of logic
that we'll have to write here in this
kind of scenario.
Yeah.
And also right,
like the way I was mentioning all these
distinct combinations here again,
once you get those combinations based on
the values,
because sometimes the other example I was
showing you, right,
maybe the non key that you have to take
to the target is still intact.
Only some other values have changed.
In this case.
It is not a real split of this particular
data if you look at what is needed into
our target, right?
So all of those nuances also has to be
accounted for while creating that query.
So deduplication,
whatever we are doing currently on the
deduplication with the hash and all,
all of that has to happen here.
Like first pick up the columns that are
needed on that perform deduplication and
identify what versions are staying out
and try to retain those versions and have
the second table as well rechange the
versions after reduplication.
Now come up with the distinct effective
dates here.
With that,
build the expiration dates and try to
identify what is the value that has to go
into the table.
OK, OK, got it.
I'll have Nikhil start on this.
Yeah.
And also one more complexity I want to
explain,
this is something that you may receive
all the data on one single day also
because there are multiple batches, right.
Maybe in the first batch you received
with 9th September to high end date,
but in the second batch itself you
received all these changes.
OK.
So there the way we are already
considering for ETL for 9th September,
we would consider this as the latest
version.
We don't we can ignore this in that case
because there are two records for the
same pro effective date when you are
reading it at once at that time you take
the latest record of it.
Yeah, OK,
See it will this thing now we'll we'll
have to iterate over this.
I don't think we'll be able to get this
correct in the first go.
We'll have to iterate over it and then
multiple people will have to review this.
Yeah, yeah.
I think if Nikhil already has idea on the
ETL,
if he has gone through those logics with
Avasti or Gayatri so far,
then he will get that.
What I was saying here.
No, no, he'll this,
this explanation is fine,
but the more permutations and
combinations that we are talking about
that will build up over time.
Yeah.
OK.
So everything he'll, you know,
will not be able to solve everything in
one go.
But yeah, but yeah, we'll, we'll see.
We'll get started.
Let's see how it goes.
Yeah.
OK.
Yeah, Yeah, OK.
Sure.
I need to draft this so that I can,
I may not give this whole detail to the
the history load pod.
They'll not be able to grasp this.
I'll just ask them about, you know,
this scenario where we have, you know,
2 driving tables or one driving table.
I'll just ask them to mark it,
at least on those ones that are needed
for Helix for now.
Right from those, yeah, objects,
whatever they have started.
And then, yeah, check on it.
Yeah.
Because, you know,
they'll not be able to solve it.
We'll have to solve it.
And then just give them the can we stop
the recording?
Yeah, Yeah, we can.
OK, now you can.
Go ahead.